[Music]
hello you found the portal
I'm your host Eric Weinstein and today I
get to sit down with one of my favorite
conversationalist Tyler Cowen who's here
from George Mason University where he's
a professor of economics Tyler welcome
to the portal thank you Eric now when we
were talking about what topics we could
begin with I didn't want to begin with
economics and you suggested the
apocalypse is a great place to start now
the great benefit of this is that if we
get past it the rest of the conversation
will be post apocalyptic the apocalypse
itself is economics of course but I was
just thinking that virtually any good
theory of politics needs some notion of
the apocalypse but say you thought the
time horizon for the universe or a human
civilization were potentially infinite
you would then be so concerned with
minimizing existential risk that nothing
would get done
whereas if you think well you know
mankind has another 800 years left on
earth on average and by that time
probably will have blown ourselves up or
an asteroid will come then you think
what glorious things can we do with
those 800 years and it's quite a
difference in perspective so an infinite
time horizon might actually choked off
rational thought about political
decision-making so is there any
possibility for keeping the apocalypse
exactly 800 years away like a donkey
with a carrot dangled in front of it at
a fixed distance that would be the
Strauss II in view right that you always
think it's 800 years away but think of
it as like a problem from from finance
so you're writing they could put on a
security well it's going to bankrupt you
at some point but any given month any
given day the chance of that happening
is probably quite small so the
apocalypse may be like the proverbial
naked put it's out there the chance is
very small the optimists always sound
like they're right in the sense they are
right as Steven Pinker would claim but
at the end of the day if the clock ticks
for long enough its boom and buy but in
the meantime let's do something grand
and glorious now Tyler you have a sort
of a portfolio of different ways of
communicating with the world
have you ever dragged Steven Pinker onto
a podcast which you do under Congress
with Tyler or have you discussed his
bizarre notion of optimism on your
famous economics blog marginal
revolutions which you do with your
colleague Alex my podcast conversations
with Tyler has an episode with Steven
Pinker and I sat him down in a chair the
way you did with me and I said Steven
the cost of destroying the world by
pressing a button is falling all of the
time every year at some point it will
only cost say twenty thousand dollars to
take out a major city how long do you
think the world is actually going to
last
given that demand curve sloped downwards
when prices fall people do more of
things destructive weaponry is becoming
cheaper how can you be optimistic I
asked him no good answer I would say
evasion he said well my theory is not
predictive it's just a way of thinking
about it uh so so it instantly falls
apart it falls apart I don't know if it
falls apart instantly because weaponry
has spread more slowly than we might
have thought so you read nuclear
theorists in the 50s and 60s they think
a third world war might be coming quite
soon they were wrong you read worries
about proliferation from the 80s and 90s
they sound horrible I wouldn't say it's
been great North Korea no one's happy
about that but at the same time the
weapons have not been used so there's
something fundamental about the models
we don't understand you can ask the
question why didn't al-qaeda hire a
bunch of Stooges to go into a Tyson's
Corner shopping mall with submachine
guns and just cause some terror that
didn't happen so the logic of choice of
wielding destructive power is one of the
issues in social science we understand
least well I would say and there is
perhaps some hope of salvation so I'm
not sure Pinker falls apart instantly
but I didn't feel Pinker defended Pinker
very well and on my blog marginal
revolution I did review his book and my
worry is that there's an observational
equivalence with how you look at the
data so you could say well deaths in
wars have been going down will continue
to fall that's possibly true but another
model is the more destructive the
weapons are the less frequent the wars
things will seem great for quite a while
but the next war when it comes will be
quite a doozy so in some sense this is
the Great Moderation which last time was
about market volatility and here it's
about the volatility of human violence
in gray
moderations maybe contain the seeds of
their own destruction well again I would
want to be cautious there because we
don't understand destructive decisions
very well like why did Hitler invade
Russia we know a lot about it in the
documented sense but I don't feel it's
understood very well agreed and I agree
that we don't know why so few reservoirs
have been poisoned yeah it was
relatively low-tech options and it the
Las Vegas shooting for example showed
what a small level of innovation in mass
killing can do to really amp the body
can if that's what somebody is trying to
optimize so I think that there is a huge
mystery but I don't think that Pinker
from what I understand of his basis for
optimism is really getting at that
people who listen to this podcast and
have heard me elsewhere have heard me
complain that it's as if he's neglecting
a potential energy term but for violence
and so the realized violence as you were
pointing out has gone down but the
potential for violence is enormous and
as the cost Falls the access to violence
of this particular nature seems to put
it into far too many within reach of far
too many hands one of our saving graces
could be that the contagion effects for
methods of violence seem pretty strong
so we're in a time where in the u.s.
shooting up schools is the thing to do
it happens more often by some metrics
than it used to in the 1970's being a
serial killer was somehow like the thing
to do so if you're inspired by what
people have done just before you and
you're not very innovative it could be
that violence and lack of innovation or
somehow correlated and contagion effects
mean you'll kill you know a terrible
number of innocent people but it still
will quite limit how much damage you do
to the world as a whole well in terms of
R&D thinking about terror innovation is
quite interesting it seems to me that
it's hard to remember that there is no
known linkage between suicide bombing
and Islam before the
the Beirut barracks bombing if I'm not
mistaken it came from Sri Lanka in the
approximate sense the idea for the
Tigers they're not the only ones who've
done I think that they didn't they
really perfected after the Beirut
barracks bombing and then it sort of
came back to the Middle East to drive
that wrong I'm not sure on the timing
but they're very few groups that have
been using suicide bombing in the modern
era yes that maybe the Kurds that the
Tamils in sri lanka
and various muslim violent movements
jihadi movements the striking thing
about 9/11 is how innovative it was
right that's what really ought to scare
us but it does seem also such
innovations are pretty scarce well in
that that in some sense at Afghanistan
was like an R&D lab for al-qaeda and one
of the things I believe I remember was
that there was a taped conversation
within al-qaeda that had leaked in which
various groups were deciding we're
trying to decide whether this was the
greatest thing they'd ever done or
whether it was a terrible move because
it was gonna cause them the loss of
their R&D let you know karl-heinz
Stockhausen the german composer he said
well it was such a wonderful work of art
and obviously he got pilloried for that
comment
i'm not sure what he meant by it it's a
terrible thing to say i wouldn't say it
but it's still getting at some aspect of
9/11 that was quite different that it
was an attempt to innovate well I mean
could we could we go there I've talked
on this program about message violence
which is violence that is made
particularly theatrical for the purpose
of underscoring a message for example
affecting a position of kindness which
clearly ends up you know torturing
somebody like you know drowning them in
a tub of their favorite wine or
something like this that there's
something very perverse about certain
kinds of violence who's where the
intention is to amplify the underlying
harm in a way that animates the
imagination in some sense you know the
Jordanian pilot video which was
cinematically
gorgeous and as sick as could possibly
be imagined that was released by Isis
would be in this realm in it is there a
sense in which we can look at 9/11 is
deliberately theatrical and artistic
most likely it was as I understand it
and if you look at the targets chosen
the World Trade Center was not actually
that economically important it certainly
was not politically important but they
were the tallest structures there is a
theory they would collapse in a certain
way and it seems they did they did so it
does seem artistically motivated in some
sense and there is this odd obsession of
many dictators with the arts which i
think is also poorly understood but it
also gets at the notion that the
totalitarian and violent impulses in US
can be severed from innovation but don't
necessarily have to be yeah you know the
passion inside of the passion play
anything that can truly excite the
spirit could easily be weaponized so
there's a way in which I guess I would
expect the dictators would be very
animated by by the theater in particular
but I think mass opinion in general
tends to neuter some of that desire for
artistic creativity so if you look at
passion plays around the world if you go
see one say during Easter in Mexico they
become something quite celebratory it's
for family and for friends and people
get together people drink people cook
special dishes so it's drained of so
much of the actual passion story and it
becomes among other things less
passionate so it's hard to sustain the
emotional violence behind the innovation
of violence and that may be another one
of our saving graces and you see this
with suicide bombers when they're
removed from their environments where
they've been indoctrinated it can be
quite hard to get them to go through
with what they've been told to do and
sometimes you get them to go through
with it by not even telling them they're
going to die hmm I've read some accounts
I'm not sure how validated this is that
a lot of the 9/11 terrorists they didn't
know they were going to die and maybe
that ambiguity I mean
presumably everybody signs up with an
idea that martyrdom is part of the
package potentially but they don't know
that the play is going to be called for
any particular Tuesday and the same was
true for RAF fighters in World War two
or any other very high-risk activity
where you're pretty sure you're one of
the good guys but you don't want to die
so the fact that it's a lottery ticket
of sorts in some ways it piques your
interest it motivates you it gets your
adrenaline up it probably improves your
performance but at the same time it's
absolutely terrifying and you know how
much does that operate symmetrically on
the good and bad moral sides of this
equation it's probably more similar than
we would feel comfortable admitting now
I ran into an idea that I hadn't heard
codified with an labeled with a phrase
before called strategic silence and I
read about this in writings or speeches
of Dana Boyd works with data and society
Institute the idea behind it is that if
you have predictable reliable news
coverage it allows somebody who let's
say wishes to undertake a terrorist
action to know that they can count on
you to amplify their message because
they have the ability to create news
they are not just news takers but news
makers in that realm the news media has
been experimenting with the idea that
they will not do the bidding of the
attacker by broadcasting things about
motive about name or about certain
circumstances of the crime so at least
ostensibly as not to amplify the
leverage of the attacker is that kind of
a death knell for confidence in
reporting that if we report the facts
straight
we give people too much leverage over
our news and if we don't report the
facts then we quickly erode confidence
in our system I favor the experiment of
not reporting the names of say mass
shooters I'm not sure we're really
withholding facts so the name of the
person didn't mean anything to the
audience and it
whether the person's name is John Smith
or John Brown it's it's a fact in some
way but in another way it's not a fact
at all whereas if it's a person who is
already known say back back then Osama
bin Laden then you are withholding a
fact if you don't say Osama bin Laden
had a role in 9/11 my worry with the
policy of strategic silence is that
destroyers will innovate in ways to
recapture the attention so if they don't
report your name maybe you kill more
people
or maybe you innovate with a new method
of killing people so you might be
inducing innovation over the medium term
and I don't think we know yet as an
experiment it does seem to me worth
trying but I wouldn't be all too
optimistic about it because as I say on
my blog like solve for the equilibrium
and what's the equilibrium here we don't
quite know although with somebody like
the Unabomber who left us a manifesto or
let's say the Christ Church shooter in
the mosque we have a fairly detailed
account of what was going through the
person's mind while they were committing
their crimes I don't know if that is
what was going through their mind it was
what was going through their mind at
some point in time but was it their
actual set of motivations I don't feel
qualified to judge but I wouldn't just
take that for granted or take it quite
literally but would you feel comfortable
and suppressing the dissemination of
such a document I don't think it's
possible to suppress that at the way the
internet and other institutions have
evolved I wouldn't do it either but in
any case it will get out there so if we
decide how it's not going to be on
Facebook as you well know there are
other parts of the internet where it
just can't be taken to an interesting
place where I think I disagree with you
I don't disagree with you that we can't
stop the document from being on the
Internet in a very determined person in
their ability to find it I do believe
that there is a frictional coefficient
that the search engines and the major
platforms can control if they so choose
to slow down the flow of information and
whether it gets reified and discussed
inside of what I've termed the gated
institutional narrative
is a big deal because those news
organizations react chiefly to each
other and special trusted institutions
and so many of us still have the idea
when we're listening to that
conversation that it's an open
conversation when if you're in a
position like you or I maybe we're
astounded by the number of things that
simply can't be discussed in in in that
echo chamber and in those corridors but
I think the short term in the medium
term are quite different here so a
Facebook and YouTube in Google all of a
sudden decide they won't cover some
awful video that will have real impact
but I think say four or five years later
there'll be some new set of tools maybe
they're only used to find the really bad
stuff but people will know there are
sites or methods where you can go see
hear experience all the really bad
things and then it still gets out so I'm
not at all opposed to people say who run
Facebook deciding not to post something
I think it's fine it's their website
more power to them but at the same time
we should not infer too much from the
short-run reaction because again solve
for the equilibrium institutions and
searchers will adjust so you and I have
a slightly different orientation but
that might be fun to play with it for a
second I think I've increased a hold a
position that these companies had the
right to do what they wanted yes and
I've started to change my opinion on
that based on the idea that if I define
the public space relative to private
space I can find only private space on
the internet I need to hire a company to
allow me to get an on-ramp in the form
of an ISP and that in general unlike a
city with parks and institutions of
government I really can't find any
public space on the Internet and so if
the whole thing is private I feel like
it's absolutely essential that we place
much more restrictive rules about what
can and cannot be prohibited on the
internet because there is no public
space from the get-go a my way and my
way off you
allergies of public and private space to
the Internet
I think are quite complex I would just
start with a very simple question who is
that you would trust in politics to make
those decisions better than what our
current Internet is giving us and for me
the answer is no one no party no
institution so I would like to keep
things more or less the way they are now
and have no liability for the internet
companies let them decide and the notion
that Congress did you see the recent
recent testimony of Mark Zuckerberg
before Congress cut a little bit of it
not much it's remarkable how little
people in Washington understand about
tech at any level so so what explains
this you and I spend a fair amount of
time in Silicon Valley and it's not like
the government couldn't get help from
the world's smartest tech people and
they can and they do but the actual
decisions are made by Congress and by a
president but what explains the lousy
level of questioning of tech people and
you know both scientific the quality of
voters right so people get the leaders
they deserve
voters are poorly informed
representatives want to parade a certain
display of toughness or strength in
front of those voters so they're
deliberately rude to Mark Zuckerberg
they ask stupid questions which voters
will let them get away with in my
Twitter feed some of the very stupidest
questions were being applauded say by
PhD economists like oh you know get
tough you know show Mark Zuckerberg so
even at that level there's an expressive
response that encourages this behavior
and that's why we get it but when you
then think gee this system is going to
regulate speech on the Internet I say no
way you know singer was right I think
that's different you ever watched
giraffes fighting or bunnies I've seen
bunnies fighting on the Internet
nobody's writing is amazing right it's
like I think I got this from Joe Rogan
bunny UFC is just Monsanto
I think people are cheering some of
these hearings in the same way that they
would cheer for like one rabbit over
another though it's like a cockfight
it's just it's just interesting watching
people beat up on each other
particularly if you like one more the
the other I don't think that people are
anywhere near as stupid as I don't think
we're getting the government we deserve
and let me give you an analogy which is
plaguing me for many things we used to
think that TV was the idiot box and we
clearly just didn't understand long-form
television of the form that has been
discovered with Game of Thrones or The
Sopranos I think that there's a
long-form politics that we want and
we're smart enough to know the
difference between what we have in that
and we can't get it because it's really
not in the interests of people who have
more leverage than the rest of us I
don't think it's the elites who are
keeping this long-form politics from us
I think it's the voters there are plenty
of candidates on the Democratic side
some of them are quite smart you may or
may not agree with them but we don't
find quite quite smart on the Democratic
side we won't talk about dumb I'm a
European and Andrew yang for instance
seem quite smart I'm not familiar with
all the candidates so if I haven't
mentioned your favorite doesn't end no
slight but they're obviously both quite
smart their chance of winning is pretty
small they have gotten media exposure I
know Andrew yang is sometimes kept out
of the CNN graphics and so and so on but
in and of itself hysterically funny as
if it's you know we're back in 1994 and
no one will be able to discuss this
because we don't have a lively internet
but the people who manipulate emotions
right are more likely to be the
Democratic candidates than those two
individuals
huh and that I don't blame on the elites
I'm not saying the elites are blameless
but it's mostly the voters do you know
Frank Luntz well I've met him and I've
heard him talk I wouldn't say I know him
well I think he's very smart I think
he's very smart too I went to college
with him and for those who don't know he
was a Republican pollster who pioneered
the use of particular phraseology for a
common concept any more or less
discovered that we don't actually have
opinions about underlying law or facts
or theory but we have huge lead
divergent opinions off based on how the
same underlying stuff is presented to us
that death taxes and estate taxes may be
the same thing but we oppose the death
tax and we're for the estate tax do you
believe that this level of emotional
manipulation would go away if we started
getting tools with which to discuss it
clearly that kind of emotional
manipulation is higher in some countries
than in others so it's impossible to
lead to believe at some fixed eternal
constant but the United States has a
long history of emotional and sometimes
populist politics in the 80s and 90s I
view as an outlier kind of era where
things were relatively calm and
reasonable even though at the time it
didn't always feel that way you feel
that way to me at all compared to the
mid to late 19th century my goodness
right yeah then you had people in
Congress attacking each other a lot of
partisan media a lot of that right line
so I don't see America becoming like
Switzerland any time soon but clearly
it's not impossible well I think one of
the things that really strikes me about
that is that the Liat waters and the
Frank Luntz is who put a sort of a
deliberate spin on this kind of
mean-spirited emotional manipulation
we're surprised that it didn't behave
let's say like rugby where you have a
bunch of gentlemen take the field play
absolutely brutally with each other and
then going back going back to being
gentlemen when the game is over Frank
Luntz has told me that he just hates the
current state state of our politics that
it's far too mean-spirited and
destructive and he can't locate anything
that he's done to kick this this listen
to high gear it's a very strange thing
there's a disconnection between working
on these campaigns in a somewhat
scientific fashion to use people's
passions to sort of take over their
decision-making and then there's this
inability to understand well how did we
all become so uncivil I wonder if one of
the problems in America is our temporal
distance
from war so there is world war two
terrible event but it did make us more
instrumental irrational and if you look
at something like the Manhattan Project
phenomenal achievement as you know done
really quite quickly would not have been
possible outside of wartime even in an
earlier America
then there's the Cold War now the Cold
War let's say it ended 1989 1992 that's
a number of decades young people today
don't know about it so without a common
enemy
maybe the enemy becomes each other in
some way and we're more mean-spirited
because there's a lack of a common enemy
that's to me the most likely single
hypothesis for what's happened and it's
evolutionarily rationale that when there
isn't a common enemy you would attempt
potentially to make your slice larger at
the expense of someone else's slice it
might might be on your team whereas
during wartime that would be seen as a
sort of an unforgivable offense because
you have something much bigger to to
organize around and I think it's
interesting the one issue where there is
at least potentially a common enemy
maybe not quite vivid yet but that would
be China sure opinion on China it's not
polarized Republican versus Democrat
I've spoken to people in Congress on
both sides about China there's a mix of
opinions diverse opinions within each
party it's not that all the Republicans
line up on one side and all the
progressives on another so there you see
polarization actually not being so
strong well I think China has done a
wonderful job of manipulating us by
making sure that most of their activity
is below a threshold so that it appears
that they don't really have any global
designs and of course there's a
narrative that says China really cares
only about China and it's not focused on
the outside world my view is China has
very strong Asian designs I'm not sure
they have truly global designs but I
view them as a threat to Liberty and
Asia sure now I guess I have a question
do you think we're living through a very
unusual time in the last this the last
decade and really probably the last five
to seven years I'm not sure I would
slice up the years that way so I now see
the
1980s and 90s as the unusual time of
calm and feeling of triumph and that
neoliberalism can do no wrong and that's
the outlier the turning point for me is
9/11 and the financial crisis and now
you have trumpism a series of very
strange events that are causing people
to revise many things they had believed
and we're responding by being nasty or
to each other so I see the cutoff point
as 2001 do you see anything for example
that's to me
I view the apparent death of Jeffrey
Epstein as one of the most bizarre news
stories I've ever seen it seemingly
happened with every bizarre coincidence
that would be necessary for somebody in
protective custody to meet his end under
a situation in which everybody wants to
know exactly who he was how he was
connected to the intelligence
communities where are his supposed
probable co-conspirators they seemed to
still be alive nobody seems to be
tracking this down the news media seems
preternatural II uninterested in it and
if you look at like top podcasts there
are lots of podcasts that are dedicated
to the Jeffrey Epstein question anybody
could make money even debunking
conspiracy theories about murders of
Jeffrey Epstein by the intelligence
community what the hell is going on that
we're not even talking about I haven't
followed the details of the Epstein
death very closely but in general it's
very hard to get me to believe in
conspiracy theories just looking at base
rates how many people kill themselves in
prison versus how many people are killed
by outside conspiracies in prison other
than the case of someone who snitches on
you know the drug gang and their shift
in the shower that kind of thing which
is pretty common so I'm not close to
thinking that was a conspiracy I would
say I have an open mind since I haven't
studied it but I don't look at it and
recoil and think my goodness this is so
strange don't I don't necessarily you
don't have to believe it's a conspiracy
you can believe that there are two
camera failures and that there's some
guards that were asleep on the job and
that a freakishly long period with
nobody killing themselves and that
facility happened to be ended because
there's an arrival of an unpredictable
event
what I write is what I believe okay
right but my point to you would be if
that's what I believed and that is a
part of what I believe it I have a
probability distribution that puts far
more weight on other things that then I
think your probability distribution does
I would be interested to discuss that
and to show people just how The
Conspirator conspiracy theorizing mind
is led astray would be a wonderful
opportunity for a rationalist to take
this on and to sell a bunch of papers by
showing what nonsense this is and even
Michael Shermer at some point but it's
the market for that so large but wanted
it's not to prove he wasn't murdered but
my point is people wanted to talk about
this much more than papers want it like
why not do it a special on what is known
about Jeffrey Epstein's connections to
the intelligence community just just
that what is known I'm not saying that
the he has huge connections the
intelligence but what do we know I read
about it in my blog comments all the
time I'm not sure how much of it to
trust but if I look back on history to
me it's remarkable how few successful
conspiracies there are and there can be
a lot of circumstantial evidence that
something was a conspiracy talk of Pearl
Harbor JFK assassination many other
cases we don't quite materialize called
a memo on Pearl Harbor affect you most
historians think it was a series of
massive screw-ups and there were clearly
pieces of information put on tables and
left around but there was no committee
or individual such as FDR saying I'm
gonna let this don't no I'm not saying
that I don't think anybody wanted Japan
to attack us you have that ferocity in
Pearl Harbor but the question of did we
want cassis bail I for World War two and
was probably and were we interested in
potentially getting torpedoed in British
shipping lanes or choking Japan which is
resource-poor for natural resources so
as to induce them into some act of
belligerence hopefully much smaller than
pro
sure but that's not a conspiracy right
that's that's a plan that went wrong
well it would be a bit of a conspiracy
to attempt to get someone to attack you
so that you could enter the war claiming
to have been attacked I don't know it
Terry strategy
well if that's in in military strategy
maybe this is the reason why you don't
see as many conspiracies because that's
just normal operating procedure
I guess I'm always shocked by how many
relatively large and complicated
conspiracies have been proven to have
existed have not fallen apart you know
all these standard things and you can't
get a large number of people to do
something without somebody squealing
that people haven't urged to purge so
nobody keeps a secret this has been to
my mind clearly disproven just by proven
conspiracy so what's what is to you the
most dramatic large-scale conspiracy
COINTELPRO has to be the best of them
and what happened there
that the FBI had a dirty tricks
department that actually fed
misinformation to create fake news into
the mainstream media with the intention
of killing law-abiding Americans because
the FBI didn't like their politics
that's pretty bad look that's a large
number of people too it's not what I see
is a conspiracy so we know for instance
as a fact that the CIA supported
abstract expressionism within the field
of painting yes because they thought it
would neutralize propagandistic art and
make America's less communistic I don't
think that's seriously disputed what I
got into a much more interesting
discussion with an economist not too
long ago who was looking at my work in
economics and said Eric the person said
to me Eric I can't stand to see you
fighting the Chicago School of Economics
do you are you aware that this was
really just a bulwark against
totalitarian communism rather than a
theory that was intended to be
operational and descriptive with
predictive power and that now that the
Cold War is over the problem is we
didn't tell the children that it was
really a political project rather than
an analytic one but I mean I know or
knew most of those people they were
economists what
said they believed was true they had
careerist concerns they wanted to make
the world a better place that's actually
the best theory of the Chicago School of
Economics well I don't know I mean you
know that there's this very funny
paradigm which I call earns as an ex
spends as a why and you know for example
in physics I would say that Edward
Witten has earned as a geometers
but he's spent as a string theorist okay
in economics I would say Milton Friedman
earned as an economist he was a very
fine connoisseur and he spent as a
political theorist and that in part this
game of earning in one place and
spending somewhere else is depending
upon how you view the history of a
subject it can be far more important to
the participants how they spend rather
than how they earn their credibility
sure look Friedman made some mistakes so
he thought that educational vouchers
would work easily and simply and be
quite popular that hasn't turned out to
be the case he was more optimistic about
shock therapy than he should have been
though I would say on the whole shock
therapy has done well on average look at
Poland right Poland is a successful
fairly free economy but what explains
that I think is just simply that Milton
didn't see the future course of world
history and he was imperfect and maybe
too optimistic about some of his own
ideas and you'll hear all kinds of
accounts about the Chicago the Chicago
boys and conspiracy or the Habsburg
monarchy you hear this from Lyndon
LaRouche okay where the CIA funded them
in Chile or whatever I don't feel those
are the correct deep historical
understandings the more or less
superficial account they had ideas they
believed in the ideas some of the ideas
were wrong a lot of them turned out to
be really quite correct their overall
record is pretty good that superficial
account I think is fundamentally true so
now that we've somehow found the
economics after burning through some
other stuff we were never out of
economics okay please continue all right
well that's the problem is that you can
never it's like you can't leave
evolutionary theory
can we talk and again let's feel free to
turn any question around on me although
I'm not an economist
what I find astounding about the field
of economics is that on the one hand I
can't get enough of it I need to use its
concepts its terminology some of its
models and on the other hand I think
it's an absolute abomination that has
been not it's not that the field is
broken so much is that the field is
fixed in the same sense that the world
series can be fixed
and I find that whenever I go into
economics there's this sort of mountain
Bailey type approach where there's this
very defensible core of economic
threatening and then there's this
absolutely tortured just so story that
we tell that almost always seems to
flatter institutions and power and and
the structures that would be upended if
we actually just let the field run and
we'll reach the conclusions that would
merge from the models it may depend on
what exactly you're being upset by but
keep in mind at least in the West what
you're calling institutions and power
are the most successful institutions the
world has seen ever so there's something
to be said on their behalf right sure
and in economics if our just-so stories
are fairly positive toward those
institutions we shouldn't be repulsed by
that there may be margins where they're
getting things wrong so I would say no
economist that I know if is really
willing to write a critique of the
National Science Foundation why is that
hard to prove but I think the logical
reasons are the obvious ones they don't
want to alienate a potential funder well
the only major critique written was
written by myself with Alex Tabarrok
other than that it's a virtually healthy
dinner i I've I've accused the National
Science Foundation of specifically
destroying the pipeline for stem labor
for the purpose of making late stem
labor cheap for employers to the
detriment of American aspire uns sure
I've read that but within economics it's
very hard to find
criticisms of the NSF virtually
impossible okay
so here's an interesting question to me
economists have been very comfortable
turning the lens of economic theorizing
on absolutely any group save one they'll
do priests they'll do it to scientists
to politicians they cannot imagine I
mean that this is going to escape notice
forever my wife has talked about
economics squared what is the political
economy of economists themselves and
where are these papers now you don't
find it interesting particularly that
this field doesn't exist I think they do
it now on Twitter so they accuse each
other of having bad motives or being
captive of their funders so with social
media you're seeing a blossoming of this
kind of attack there are still
criticisms I don't like being made so
there's the partisan criticism of people
who disagree with you but to say
criticized Chinese graduate students
because they can't speak their mind
about issues related to China because
they fear for their own careers or for
their family members back in China that
somehow not acceptable to raise even as
an issue so I do think there are big
blind spots but just like attacking the
other person is now pretty common
typically done in a not very clever
sophisticated way okay but we let's talk
about making it clever or more
sophisticated if you were going to turn
the lens of economics and particularly
the analysis of political economy on the
profession of economics what would be
the assuming that there's sort of a
Pareto curve here sure for the first ten
percent of my effort I should get
something like seventy percent of the of
the bang what would be the first thing
to do in economic theory using economic
theory against economists themselves
well you use the subjunctive but I have
in fact written this the biggest problem
is people over specialize and right
narrow defensible papers to be published
that are invulnerable to peer criticism
but don't amount to very much and
there's a massive waste of human labor
and people do not direct their energy
energies toward actually solving
problems
answering questions not to me is
criticism number one I think it's
absolutely correct it concerns me
greatly a small number of people have
voiced this that's sort of a if I
understood it correctly and perhaps I
didn't that's a little bit of an
opportunity cost that we could have done
a lot more and instead we settled for
something that wasn't or maybe those
people should just not be doing
economics they're talented people they
could just you know build bricks
whatever true but if I think about what
really moved the needle in medicine
let's say the the whole concept of
iatrogenic harm which is you know harm
done by healers really focused us on the
idea that certain hospitals kill more
people than others
what about ikana genic harm it depends
at whom you point the finger but if you
look at what is sometimes called the
Washington Consensus which is not of you
I completely agree with by any means but
it's called the Washington Consensus for
a reason there's a recent paper by Bill
easterly that goes through and argues
correctly I think that uh Navarrete the
Washington Consensus has done more good
than harm so the idea that economics is
some great scandal that we've gone
around wrecking things Benjamin
Applebaum argues this in his recent book
I like that book I think it's small
right but I think it is more wrong than
right and it's overlooking the many
cases where economic advice has done
well I mentioned Poland before but Czech
Republic Slovakia you look at Chile
which has been democratic since 1990
economic inequality in Chile has been
falling for some period of time the
country started from sky-high rates and
it has fallen somewhat it's in the
middle of the Latin American
distribution but it's fallen and the
country as the highest real wages in
Latin America by some amount it's not a
miracle it's not perfect economists gave
some bad advice there but overall they
did much more good than harm see this is
the thing that I I'm very confused by I
understand let me just say that I cede
that even though economists may do a lot
of harm prettified as doing pure good
that that's not the criticism that I
would really level first at the
profession it's really something closer
to academic malpractice where the
economists know the truth the right way
to set up the problem and choose not
only not to do that in public but to
demonize to exclude to blackballed
anyone who would make the correct
critique in other words they don't know
the right way to set up the problem we
don't we're too stupid what's the
problem we should be setting up let me
give the the the the example that I
perhaps know I know a small number are
we gonna get to gauge theory now you
want to well first make your point but
at some point we need to get to gauge
theory because I need you to for a
little of each I'll change one I'll do
the gauge I'll do a gauge Theory example
but that's complicated do your other
simpler point then we'll do gauge Theory
well I could do the Great Moderation I
could do stem labor and I could do CPI
these are things I've I've engaged with
if I did the CPI one that's very clear
you have a small number of economists
who in the mid-90s became directed by
Bob Packwood and Daniel Moynihan to find
an overstatement of the CPI because tax
brackets were indexed right and
entitlement benefits Social Security
Medicare were indexed and so what they
found is if you could knock down the
measurement of the CPI you could raise
taxes and slash benefits and they backed
out that 1.1 percent overstatement
if corrected would lead to a trillion
dollar savings over ten years and they
actually broke into two groups to come
up with two separate numbers that would
add together to 1.1 which to me is
academic malpractice that is they
started with the target and this is
according to one of their own members of
this Boskin Commission
professor Gordon who talked about the
fact that somehow the two groups came up
with the two numbers which would added
together gave Dale Jorgenson a Harvard
professor of economics as 1.1%
overstatement and that's what they went
with not to me that's like saying we
need to find an error in all the
temperature gauges so that we can come
up with different targets because global
warming is a problem you're not allowed
to touch the temperature gauges for
God's sakes for sure as in so many
numbers there's an error of exaggerated
exactness but if you look say at
Google's price index it's not so
different from how we calculate the CPI
if you look at how central banks or
other economic authorities around the
world calculate their CPI's it's not
that different than what we have done
and you could say it's all one big
overly correlation or a conspiracy but I
don't see that the current way of
calculating the CPI is off by very much
and if it's off it still may be
overstating inflation a wee bit because
there are perhaps more free goods today
through the internet than we had in time
that sound it's not a legitimate
counter-argument what I'm trying to say
is is that assume that in fact there is
a best CPI and assume that it was one
one percent overstated it's still not
legitimate to go into a quiet room in a
closed Commission and say here's the
target boys we have to find this number
let's break into groups and put together
that number so that our finding will
raise taxes and slash benefits you're
not allowed to break the gauge to get
the policy the gauge is the gauge
politics is an ugly system but it does
seem they gave us a measure of the CPI
somewhat better than what we had had if
you think that inflation has actually
been much higher you must think real
rates of return today are astonishingly
low I mean that will truly make you a
mega pessimist which perhaps you are but
keep in mind people compare our
measurements of rates of inflation to
other economic variables and see if the
whole picture makes sense and if you
think the true rate is very different
from what we have that implies some very
radical conclusions which I don't want
to dismiss out of hand but I'll just say
there are multiple checks on this broad
do they fit in with our other I think
we're in two different layers of the
discussion which is fascinating to me
one layer the discussion is did they
point out some good things about ways in
which the CPI could be done better they
did and did they do some work they
absolutely did did they commit academic
malpractice absolutely motherfucking yes
they committed academic malpractice it's
not in the same layer of the stack Tyler
to me it is your objection just the
process so I don't doubt yeah bad things
went on in those rooms I don't know I
wasn't there
well they destroyed my wife's career
over it as my opinion they went into
something called the Harvard jobs market
meeting which is a closed-door session
during the time that the Boston
Commission was active and she was
talking about two of the things that you
can do to try to adjust the CPI to make
it more accurate one is to replace
what's called a mechanical index that is
something that prices let's say a basket
of goods in two different time periods
famous examples being the posh and lost
pairs index that you can either replace
that with a human standard which is like
cost-of-living what is the cost to make
you equally happy between two points in
time right or you can do something
called chaining and chaining given that
your blog is called marginal revolution
marginal revolution was originally the
introduction of the differential
calculus in the economic theory and this
is in the limit an application of
differential calculus and the fact is
that these two things have never played
well together because you can't chain
tastes in economic theory you have this
doctrine that says the tastes have to be
treated as if they were unchanging and
what we did in collaborative work was to
bring engage theory as you were
sustaining to make sure for the first
time you had dynamic agents who were
allowed to change their tastes as humans
do and still stay within the folds of
what's known as ordinal utility theory I
would say this most people would admit
and indeed emphasize that over
I'm period of multiple decades the
comparisons just don't work and cannot
work there are various impossibility
theorems for aggregating price indices
over time so if you ask what would you
rather hand me like the Ragnar Frisch
--is right would you rather have fifty
thousand dollars to spend in the Sears
Roebuck catalog of today or nineteen
hundred most people would rather spend
it in the catalogue of today but that
suggests there's actually been radical
deflation but I don't think that's
exactly the correct conclusion I think
the correct conclusion is over very long
periods of time the comparability goes
away in transitivity enters into the
calculation and you just need to be very
careful and modest as to what you know
and don't know actually there's an
entirely different possibility so what
we're discussing for those of you at
home would want to play along one of the
things that's weird about this podcast
is that I'm very willing to throw out
pointers rather than to dumb things down
to the point that nothing ever happens
on the podcast so there was a guy named
Irving Fisher who you can look up who
came up with lots of axioms to find the
perfect price index and then Ragnar
Frisch came up with an impossibility
theorem that said if you took on
Fisher's axioms there was provably no
measure that could satisfy all of the
axioms impossible all right okay now let
me ask you about gauge theory for before
you tell us what it is
give us the bottom line you know money
shot let's say gauge theory is correct
is the actual rate of inflation higher
or lower than what we're measuring you
know it's that you're measuring the
wrong object there's something that you
would create which you might so if we
previously use these mechanical posh and
les pairs in this indices those are
replaced by something called a CONUS
index now CONUS comes in two flavors but
it's a cost of living which prices
utility the pleasure I get from items
rather than the cost of the items so if
wine and beer are the same price per
litre and I'm a different between them
right and there's a frost that kills off
a bunch of grapes if you pay me the
money to rebuy my original basket I'm
going to take the money I'm going to buy
a mess of beer because wine is
come to expense that I'm gonna spend the
extra money on something else right so
if you want to get rid of that effect
you've moved to this thing called the
conus index and you adjust for quality
better but that's hard to do there's a
lot of people well there's a lot of
integrity mystics who try to do this
right it's a highly imperfect and okay
the internet makes it harder but that's
not that's not where gauge Theory really
comes in what the the really exciting
thing about gauge theory and economics
and there's nobody I'd rather discuss it
with and then Tyler is that economics
should be the most interesting of
subjects analytically and intellectually
because it is the only place that I'm
familiar with man's two greatest ideas
coming into direct contact the theory of
selection both sexual and natural that
governs us as Apes which we don't use
very much but continually it's a great
idea I think if you allow a
reinterpretation in which let's say
utility maps to Fitness and indifference
maps to drift I think you'll find that
you're using it everywhere in fact what
economics does is to give you a second
layer using the fact that money uniform
eise's a lot of things to allow and as
if physics to arise as in the work of
Paul Samuelson and so the weird thing is
is that you've got Apes engaging in
markets which is really just selection
by other by other means
using and as if physics as the language
of interaction so you I would say the
best idea of economics is that demand
curve sloped downwards price goes up
people do less of something a selection
is an incredibly important idea we've
done a bad job of incorporating it no
slight meant to the idea there's a lot
of pieces on selection in economics but
they tend to be big sprawling messes
rather than useful and most of the best
economics pieces are based on pretty
simple applications of the law of demand
or income effects but to get back to
gauge Theory let's say everything you're
saying is true is the actual real rate
of return higher or lower than I used to
think it is that's what I want to know
should I be more optimistic or more
pessimistic no my guess is you probably
end up more pessimistic but the
number of different things that would
change you see there's a concept let's
say in computer programming about how
something is caste if I have the number
three I can either treat 3 as a symbol
in which case it's a string I can treat
it as an integer in which case I'd call
it an you know int or I could treat it
as a float 3.000 and however much
accuracy that the computer is willing to
maintain the question of what is let's
say a representative consumer is not
properly understood in my opinion I
agree that the the problem is the
representative consumer should be afield
something like a temperature field or a
field of wind measurements on the space
of all possible consumers now you and I
will explore hopefully on this podcast
something about our difference in taste
and music I don't even know what it is
but we're gonna shut it down we're gonna
find out it is the case that if you were
doing inflation properly you would be
using gauge theory and you would you be
using field theoretic concepts for
representative agents you wouldn't be
making these point like it you would
never say what's the temperature today
in America because it's it's it's you've
cast temperature which should be a field
displayed on a map as if it was a single
number like a float okay but again let's
say you're right what's the actionable
trade based on this information I mean
you probably are already rich but you
should be truly truly rich right because
there'll be an actionable trade if we're
miscalculating rail rates of return well
even if there's variance if the proper
estimate is higher than we realize
there'll be some kind of options play on
that and over time it will
systematically make money I mean I think
that my my reluctance is is that it's
not really a sharp question you have all
sorts of questions like hedonic
adjustments which is you know the car
that I call a Mustang today isn't like
the car that I call a Mustang from 30
years ago so I may have to look at how
much luxury trunk space fuel efficiency
that series of different objects had and
as its as it changed qualitatively
there's a question about why does
economics
focus so much on Pareto improvement as a
gold standard where if you all get rich
by an additional billion dollars and I
get rich by 35 cents I'm supposed to say
that I'm improved any sensible human
being looking at things like mate
selection or you know scarce vacation
property will know that I'm much worse
off I wouldn't agree with that but
that's a separate question but that's
that there's so many of those things I
don't know how to answer your question
in other words the field but you should
be short in tangible capital if you
think true real rates of return are
lower than other people realize and
maybe tangible capital you can measure
exactly how valuable the factory is but
intangible capital which is hard to
value you should be more pessimistic
about so there's a bunch of firms with a
lot of intangible capital you could
short those if you want to be hedged the
market as a whole you could be long or
otherwise protect yourself against other
developments by having some other long
people except it's also the case that
some of us who have attempted to form
these kind of broad theses I can tell
you that I didn't really appreciate what
was going to happen between the collapse
of Bear Stearns and in several months
after AIG was about to sure hardened
basically no one did even people who saw
some parts of the crash early on did not
have good day by day predictions of how
it would all unfold well and the issue
of the interceding in the markets you
know with a very visible hand to engage
in pure acts of political economy to you
know both stabilize the economic system
but also to defend very vulnerable
institutional players I no longer know
how to make those kinds of trades
because I don't believe that I know what
we can do artificially in the face of a
crisis but if real rates of return are
truly lower than is believed the system
cannot deny that either forever or even
for that low that's right claiming that
we're just keep on buying puts on the
appropriate stocks don't do it with
leverage just toss money into those
trades forget about them do it for 30
years
your
young man maybe you're doing it right
I'm not expecting you to tell the
audience your financial position I'm
just saying there's a way of testing
this view it's not that hard
most people in the hedge fund world are
not doing this right and they think very
closely
why do believe that we are Asian I
believe there's about a 50 year bubble I
mean so one of the thing that that
unites us is I was thrilled that you
were all so focused on the early 1970s
as a real and mysterious discontinuity
with respect to growth and it's one of
the biggest puzzles so 1973 comes a lot
of indicators crash you can say fine the
higher price of oil that's great but the
higher price of oil goes away and those
indicators do not come back very well
what do you think okay first of all
let's just do this slowly sure is it
mysterious that more people aren't
focused on what happens around 1972 to
74 of course 10% of the profession
should be working on that instead people
are doing these little narrow things to
publish but it's hard to get a clear
answer to the question we're discussing
so no one can publish on it the referees
will shoot down whatever you turn in I
would rather see people just write and
speculate on the more important
questions but if you ask what do I think
happened clearly oil was a major factor
let me give you just a little bit of
your do what you can't do but I can yeah
I think my favorite version of the graph
that shows how violent this change was
is something that you focused us on it's
not perfect but it's measured GDP
whatever the failures we have of that
measure together with measured male
median income yes and those two things
are going up in lockstep before 1973 or
so and then one of them flatlines and
the other keeps going up
does that graph something that you
developed I presented it obviously the
numbers come from other people I've done
a lot to draw attention to it but I
don't pretend it's original with me well
I think it's I think was a great
observation that that graph was so clean
that it caused people to stop denying
that something happened her and then
they almost immediately in my experience
and correct me if the if yours is
different they go from not believing
that something really big happened to
immediately telling you exactly what it
was that happened that explains it and
they're rich people stole at all or
something yeah or it's all about Bretton
Woods or it's all just about the oil
shock but I think the missing variable
once you get through oil prices
over-regulation a number of factors that
people have already discussed but I
think the increasing feminization of
society is a missing factor in this
whole equation that norms have changed
women as a whole
or more risk-averse we're much less
likely to fight a war in a more
feminized society so in my opinion this
is very likely good on net but change is
harder to accomplish in some ways and
people are more comfortable with higher
levels of regulation and that's how
things are there's pluses and minuses
but it will slow down measured economic
growth now can we talk about to use your
term a feminized economy without in a
public in a public sphere without having
to celebrate everything that is
feminized and demonized everything that
was lost well it depends who the we is
okay I do think one should consider
costs and benefits and to a large extent
men have accepted a more feminized
society because it has very strong
positives so I'm completely sincere when
I say on that I think it's a good thing
so give me those experimental evidence
and portfolio evidence women are more
risk-averse and as a norm my guess is
not proven but my speculation is that
really matters and it is in addition to
other factors about productivity in
regulation and spending more in fighting
pollution and oil prices and so on which
are at this point more or less
well-known and that's why I think the
slowdown has mostly persisted and I do
think you will have extraordinary
periods like 1995 to 1998 when
information to
nology to so many good things it
overwhelms the negatives I think we'll
have more of those so let's assume for
the moment that both feminization of
some kind has occurred right and let's
also just stipulate for this purpose
that it's also net positive right up
until the present let's imagine that
going forward far fewer women choose or
are able to form families and become
mothers sure how does that change the
equation potentially could that tip this
increased level of feminization negative
well could it even now forgetting about
the speculation it's a significant gain
for elite men and quite possibly a
negative for non elite men and you see
that in the data very clearly due to
marriage correct so marriage as an
incentive is much weaker for some
subclass of men who seem to be fairly
numerous religiosity seems to be down
total fertility is down it's now I
believe it about 1.8 it used to be a 2.2
and if you look at social indicators for
a lot of men in the lower middle class
income or educational category you see
massive problems and that's part of the
story what sorts of economic behavior
do you see change with let's say lower
status males really taking the brunt of
some of the shocks to to our modern
economy well marriage is good for man on
net it feminized 'iz them for one thing
greater health lower depression correct
less drug abuse suicide rates lower and
so on and we're seeing those variables
for significant numbers of men move in
the wrong directions median income as
you noted as I presented that has been
stagnant for the median male earner I
think those numbers are across a long
enough period of time they're unreliable
in some ways but that there is a problem
is completely indisputable to say oh
it's gone up exactly so much between
1970 and today that is an illusion but
that it is a problem and indeed a crisis
that is very much a reality
and you see it again in many other
indicators not just the income numbers
that's how we know it's real
what have women potentially lost from
increased feminization even if it's net
positive for them as well again women is
quite a large category times men would
you want to break it up into low status
and high status females looking at some
of the issues about how high status
females use low status females
to perform kin work that would otherwise
have to be done I mean if there's
evidence that stress levels for a fair
number of women are higher if you think
women now have the chance to have better
careers
which is great for the economy and very
good for the person working if you're in
a career you enjoy but at the same time
it may be hard to convince the men they
should take on a greater share of
child-rearing responsibilities so the
woman ends up having to do both and the
income level is higher but the stress
level is much higher and I think there's
both scientific evidence and anecdotal
evidence that is true I couldn't tell
you offhand how large a class of women
that is but I do know it's been studied
pretty extensively why do you think it's
so difficult to discuss costs and
benefits and even the facts of gender
within economic theory without it
becoming so contentious as to
effectively make the at a price on what
it profitable well it's hard to discuss
in many settings not just in economics I
think actually economics is one of the
better settings to be able to have such
discussions there were two areas in
academia where you can still say things
are either counterintuitive or possibly
politically incorrect and that's
economics and philosophy and both are
healthier for it so to me that
evolutionary theory I know that area
less well may well be true I would say
that that's probably my I mean it's
under a ton of pressure no don't get me
wrong but I do think that if you allow
political correctness in to evolutionary
theory there is no subject
probably true again I couldn't say
economics is under some pressure now but
it's so dated driven that results get
out right they may be reframed in
particular ways or certain angles of it
talked down or putting do any thoughts
about the wage gap well which one
between men and women let's take though
if you adjust for demographics it mostly
goes away I do think there is also
discrimination against women in labor
markets but I don't know huge measured
by the wage gap well that's that's one
of my problem like I've gone so far as
to claim that academic tenure is
increasingly withheld because a large
number of females find child-rearing so
fulfilling that it competes even if
they're at the very top of their
profession as researchers and so by
forcing people both men and women to
wait longer and longer for a permanent
job offer what you do is you start
selecting out against a very talented
usually female assistant professor who
may discover the joys of raising three
kids and will have a fifteen year period
of decreased productivity I've argued we
should abolish tenure to be more fair to
women there are other reasons but that
allow you think that that's somewhat
lands me absolutely the frustration
being that those of us who think of
ourselves as concern with actual
discrimination against women in the
labor force may not want to sign on to
the you know women get paid seventy five
cents for every dollar that a man gets
paid because that's not a good argument
and the elite men who benefit from ten
year they'll just call it meritocracy
and somehow compartmentalize and not see
how it's an unfair system but another
thing I would say that I would really
want to stress there's a lot of kind of
tough talk unlike the right wing about
oh the claims of women about
discrimination are overblown or
incorrect and so on and I get where
they're coming from but the
discrimination against women in markets
it's very real it's very significant and
our main self-image of ourselves should
be as problem solvers who will reduce
that discrimination and take on some
kind of emancipatory perspective
to do that I think you have to be
objective about the evidence but the
goal is not at the end of it all to
dismiss it or the Democrats are wrong or
the left-wing is terrible it's really
the wrong proach like focus on the
individuals there's a big problem tell
people to come at it from a different
perspective I say come at it from greed
if you imagine the number of insights
that are held between female ears and
putting up extra barriers within the
workplace means that we have less we
have fewer minds that we can query it
definitely seems to me the case
that given differential success rates if
you believe in anything like
intellectual equality there should be a
bonanza to be unlocked from having women
highly productive in the workplace to me
I mean to me greed rather than
obligation seems to me to be the right
strategy and not everybody loves that
approach yes but there is a collective
action problem so even if you as an
individual say an employer are greedy
there may be social norms that make it
hard for you to benefit from your
insights yeah because the other people
in your workplace customers may have
screwed up expectations and norms and
you can't just wave a magic wand and
kind of see through all the myths of
gender and hire the right people and
automatically succeed there's some
educational issue a collective action
problem where large numbers of us need
to understand what's going on better and
see which are the actual discriminations
which I think are often matters of
expectations and role models and
implicit biases which can be very strong
well you asked about gauge Theory
earlier when we ran into trouble trying
to introduce gauge Theory into the core
of economics it was gonna have a very
unpredictable effect because it was
going to be a backwards incompatible I
was sorry a backwards compatible upgrade
of the entire theory with making
compatible also with the world's most
beautiful mathematics found in particle
Theory general relativity and
differential topology what I found was
that their economics was set up for it
to be a battle and that my wife and
collaborator did not want the fight and
I was I mean I was just ready to
you know to duke it out with these guys
for the pure pleasure of shoving it down
their throat is an extremely sort of
male aggressive perspective on an
innovation and because it was under her
name given that it was her thesis and we
would collaborate it on part of it there
was no ability to actually have that
fight so that the the norms of the
profession favored conflict as a means
of exploring something and that because
women may have different feelings about
how conflict should be handled I worry
that like in this instance where you
know you had somebody from from the
developing world who's female presenting
a new idea that such ideas can get lost
very easily if we don't have a more
balanced workplace there's a lot of
self-examination going on in economics
right now about conflictual norms and
how seminars are held but I worry a bit
will address the superficial aspects and
be superficially slight concern and not
change actually being rival risks in the
way that is screwed up we'll see how it
evolves this is a new movement but so
far I'm not yet optimistic that we'll
get at the actual problem you aren't
well we'll see in all fairness the
people who raise it are completely
correct to raise that I'm on their side
but at the same time we can't be naive
you've got to realize problems are
deeply rooted and to just focus on the
superficial symbols of the problem you
can end up not fixing things
so we've referred to this podcast as
audio and video samizdat that
effectively this is pirate radio for a
new generation you were famous with in
economics for a couple of moves that
seemed really nutty to me and I think
the first one is that you turned down
Harvard to go to George Mason as an
undergraduate because you thought you
could spend more time reading the grains
that create works of economics as do I
have my facts moral
right I didn't apply to Harvard I had a
very strong academic record oh and this
was back in the late 1970s I'm believe I
could have gotten into many top schools
though but I only applied to George
Mason in fact okay so my high school
guidance counselors thought I was crazy
I had SATs you know the time and so on
good grades but for me this was a
version of homeschooling I was choosing
homeschooling and most of all I hated
the idea of living in a dorm I
considered that so barbaric that is a 17
year old I thought I want a life I want
a car I want an apartment George Mason
was a commuter school it had an
interesting economics department but
most of all I wanted my personal space
an ability for classes not to be too
hard or have too much homework and I
would just work on my own like every day
all day long morning through night and I
did it was it a great decision well it's
not for me to say I don't regret it at
all I'm very happy I did it but you know
great by what standard it could be a lot
of decisions you make ex-post you're
glad you're turned out to be you and
you'll endorse them but that's not quite
as informative as actually seeing the X
on tape trade-off okay but then you you
went to Harvard for grad school correct
and it was necessary for me to get a job
right and then a research job and then
you came back to George Mason after a
stint at UC Irvine that's correct okay
and you start choosing to blog
yes that's correct that was I think 2003
though my memory could be off by okay
now this puts you in a group with people
like Peter White in physics who are
starting to really upset standard acted
emissions if I recall correctly because
the power of this blog to up end what
had been thought to be the meritocracy
if you have somebody who can think and
write very clearly in an in a lively
fashion suddenly they're able to have a
different kind of influence than you
might have through a journal like
econometric or something like that but
I'm not sure I upset people at first it
was not taken at all seriously so no one
was upset and then it was very quick all
of a sudden that it was taken very
seriously and then
people decided they needed to suck up to
me or to the blog and there was not much
of an intermediate period or I fought
some kind of war it goes opposite I
didn't understand that so in general the
power of this blog once it was realized
cause people to want to get along with
you people are very nice to me as I
think they should be but they're not
always nice to each other they're nicer
to me than they are to each other huh
and that came suddenly and before that
happened they just ignored me there was
never much hostility that I'm aware of
well I tried fighting you on a couple of
points but I was very ineffectual so I
can see that you're I don't I don't
still really likeable I don't feel I'm
one of these people who's had to fight
off this incredible opposition and you
know I persevered and they told me this
and I stuck with it that doesn't ring so
true to me it was like I did my own
thing world bike who knows but they
weren't paying attention and then
somehow magically it worked out and what
do you think the current status of
economics blogging I mean I just
most of the blogs have faded and have
died who's still in it that that's worth
reading it depends what you count as a
blog but econ log with Bryan Caplan
Scott Sumner and other people is great
Scott summoner's own blog is very good
Arnold cling ask blog it's called PO
Krugman is not really blogging anymore
the debates happen on Twitter which i
think is a less effective medium but
obviously it's quicker and in that sense
quote unquote cheaper and obviously
Facebook Twitter and other social media
have beaten out blogging it's been great
for my efforts we've played a kind of
last-man-standing strategy and done very
well with it so I'm not worried about
the death of blogging my view is like
bring it on you know just the death of
Tyler Cowen that way but until then you
know blog will continue just ask the
question how many websites can you go to
every day where there's reliably
interesting content see this New York
Times there's Financial Times there's a
bunch of others well do you think the
comment section of marginal revolutions
your blog is a large draw I don't know I
think it's pretty terrible I hope it's
not a large draw but since it has a lot
of comments it must draw someone it does
seem to draw a lot of interest for
people
you want to mix it up there I don't know
whether you will provide context for the
post so I shut down the comment section
for like ten days just as an experiment
yeah and all these people wrote me
they're like we know the comments were
terrible but they gave us context on
your post because you would just say
things we wouldn't understand and we'd
read the comments and now we know what's
at stake so now I think those people are
doing something pretty valuable even
though like the actual quality of what
is said is highly variable to be
generous do you have the sense that
we're part of a weird movement of I
don't know how to call it like thinkers
who aren't much recognized by the
standard structures like the standard
struggles diet you are not like you're
you're like Patrick Collison for example
as somebody who a lot of our world that
I share with you holds and very high we
hold him in very high esteem I don't
know how many people in the country
think of Patrick as a mind rather than
as a very rich CEO Patrick is one of the
smartest people ever but I think a whole
bunch of people know that now yeah and
do you think that he's being tasked by
our government to really think through
difficult problems in technology I would
I would desk him an art be well I don't
know what our government has in mind but
I want to get back to this idea of like
who are the structures so marginal
revolution it's a blog but I don't view
it as just about me I view myself as
editing a daily magazine for economists
and other smart people right and like
it's the daily magazine for economists
and related kinds of thinkers so I don't
view it it's like an outside thing
anymore I know it has this funny weird
early years of blogging look like a
1990s web site that's like a retro
inside joke it's so cool I like it yeah
yeah and I don't even know how to make
it better without it looking kind of
stupid and gross but uh like I'm the
establishment but the only part of it
okay so you're gonna pretend to be the
establishment you can attack me now
right well who are the best heterodox
thinkers that
live sort of on the periphery of the
consciousness I don't know what - okay
the term I'm serious you absolutely I
wrote a blog post about you uh and I
said it he defended for this podcast I
didn't just defend it defend you I said
Eric Weinstein is one of the most
interesting people to sit down and have
an extended intensive conversation with
this is why it's so hard to fight with
you it you couldn't be kinder but I'm
trying to think about whose signal we
can boost at the moment like I think you
remember we went to that meeting on how
to think about measuring Andrew and
reforming science for higher
productivity Laura Deming for example
blew me away I thought she had sorry
it's great she had some of the best
insights III don't know how to boost her
signal enough she's she's somebody like
Patrick that I want more people thinking
about we have a mutual friend who is
incredibly generative and very dangerous
Michael Vassar intellectually I'm never
sure what's up with Michael I've spent
time with him and been very impressed
but I just don't know what he's doing
yeah you enlightened me no bad sign
right or you know what no no I can tell
you that he's theorizing about woke as a
concept he's much more for it without
buying it in its own terms that sounds
like me but what are his intermediate
product don't know I mean it's just
there are these people who many of us
talked to over the years or grin you
must know who grant is no you don't know
grand just GW e RN just Google two grand
he is a man you see like the Daniel
schmuck Dan burger of our time when this
Rutenberg I don't but I you will the way
you put the question yeah so Gwen lives
in Southern Maryland okay
and just like lives and he writes these
essays on the internet and he collects
information he's a phenomenal guy very
friendly if you meet him seems super
nice I don't know him well but I've only
positive things to say about my
interaction with him and his essays will
blow your mind
yeah it's God Alexander but this I smell
okay so the slates dark coat
there's no longer heterodox or orthodox
any more ideas come from the internet
whether everyone likes that or not okay
for the last 10 15 years and the people
we're all discussing are in various ways
significant players on the Internet and
of course it's diverse but they're not
like quite the Outsiders anymore and
neither are you
oh really i'li I don't know that I can
get my ideas inside of the institution
my claim is is that when the heterodox
thinkers are finally invited back in
like I think you want to be invited the
Council on Foreign Relations they would
bore the hell out of you not the way I'd
do it I don't know I mean I'm sure
they're fine they have a lot of smart
people I know a lot of people that are
like them very much I enjoy talking with
them I've never visited the place okay
but as an institution yeah I don't think
of them as changing anyone's mind on
anything yeah and I don't mind no but
that's part of what I think about like
the National Academy of Sciences I went
for a meeting at the National Academy
and it's very clear that they weren't
used to really heterodox ideas of a
certain level in anything like the
volume that we had them and the problem
that I so I have this thing I call the
disc the distributed idea suppression
complex yeah and it has to do and this
has to do with our mutual friend Peter
Thiel who has a related bizarre version
of a common idea that that we've talked
a lot about his version is that the
stagnation that he and I and you I think
have all discussed is actually
functional that it's really important to
retard the spread of great ideas because
in some sense they may be so
destabilizing to a fragile world
fascinating idea it's a fascinating idea
Peter I would say would be one of the
smartest people of our age and again too
often he's referred to us of like maybe
I was weird yeah he's really really
quite good as an original creative
generative thinker and as a judge of
talent which are two related but
separate things well it's like Peter
could be the smartest person that I know
well in part to make that argument what
I would say is is the
Peter does a better job figuring out who
the generative heterodox thinkers are
your objection notwithstanding to the
term heterodox and then what he realizes
very often is is that they don't know
the the best way of putting forward
their ideas
he's also got another idea that
academics don't understand which I call
maximally compressed minimally distorted
where he takes some idea and he's
willing to give up a tiny amount of
accuracy to make it extremely compact so
that when unpacked it tells you a ton
and because academics over focus on
special cases he very often runs the
table where somebody will object to the
idea that his principal isn't exactly
accurate but it's thematically so
accurate that the heuristic is just
about over whelming power and of course
he's used that to enrich himself quite
considerably Patrick Collison may be the
quickest learner but I would say this
Eric enjoy your triumph so we live in
this funny in-between world where the
old structures are all still there and
we both have had the first half or so of
our lives in only the old structures yes
second half of our lives in the world of
the internet we're the only generation
that will be able to say is a beautiful
point it's beautiful but when the old
structures fade away and you have more
and more people who just grew up with
the internet like you are the mainstream
and the Council on Foreign Relations
it's like the heterodox thinkers who
don't have much influence and I'm half
teasing you yeah but in fact I'm mostly
correct and you just don't see it yet
because these kind of status hangover is
still there they have like the thick oak
desks whatever in there all I said we
want that it's not that at all it has to
do with the fact that I've been in both
worlds you know I've been I've been at
Harvard and MIT and Oxford and I've also
been shit out of luck and the
oscillation between being in the good
graces and outside of the good graces
has impressed me a great deal I think
more than than it has with you because
you've just charted a heterodox path
I've never been out of the good graces
yeah I've just been ignored at times
I've never felt like the stress
so the failure well okay I guess in
terms of opportunity costs a lot of us
view you as one of the most insightful
and encyclopedic minds out there you do
an unbelievable job of sifting for us
and you're an unbelievable expose eater
and we would we would naturally see you
as at the very highest echelon and I
think that view is now much much more
widespread than it was 15 years ago
right I mean you've become time has
treated you pretty well it's gone well
for me yeah like if I'm just out in the
world and I don't like go out to place
as much yeah just once a week someone
will recognize me or like more than once
a day someone will write me and like
Express great let's go some clubbing on
the Sunset Strip people are gonna
recognize you all I'm not sure that's
the place me but uh I've had a lot of
good fortune I would say so let's talk
about something you're talking about
being 17 attic choosing to go to a
commuter school you were playing guitar
back then I think I've started when I
was 11 or 12 yeah and I quit like around
the time I was 17 because I went to
college and your musicianship informed
you in terms of what the structure of
music really is at its deepest level you
have strong opinions about music and
culture I was always terrible on guitar
I wanted to learn different fields of
music and I thought to do that you
needed to play something yeah understand
basics of music music theory chords
whatever so I did a bit like classical
jazz blues every different kind of
guitar just a bit to have an entry point
into the world of music it was never to
play or impress people or I ever played
for people and was never good but I
could play the notes of a song to see
how it fit together okay there is a kind
of relativism that has descended over
musical tastes where every time I say
something is better than something else
I run into somebody instantaneously
telling me I've committed like I get a
traffic citation that you can't say
you know that that Bach is much more
important or better than scarlotti and I
just don't understand this complete
abdication of any role in which you know
informed judgment plays a role that we
have to have issues of taste that that
say this is better than that and then
you're allowed to take a look you're
allowed to take a heterodox position on
that but we should be passing along our
tastes and our prejudice and exposing it
to discussion with other people rather
than just finding relativist motion and
I think the relativists often don't mean
it what they're really saying is on
objective grounds I challenge the status
of the person making this Proclamation
and I will challenge the status by not
accepting the judgement but they're not
actually claiming that all yours in
these are relativistic I don't think of
postmodern or relativism are these
booking and the way jordan peterson says
i've never bought that argument in
Peterson's exchange with z zack and
their debate
I thought Peterson lost that part of the
debate
most people are Objectivists whether
they admit it or not let's just say what
we think is correct and debate it and
David Hume in the mid 18th century wrote
some wonderful essays on standards of
taste in the test of time I think he was
essentially correct that matters of the
aesthetics are not objective in the same
way that matters a fact are that you can
measure and confirm them but nonetheless
there is something about the judgments
that informed people make that expresses
an interest objective validity and it
can be debated and judged and it's one
of the things we're here on earth to do
so time taken wonderful music what moves
what moves your soul in music well let's
start with classical music my tastes are
completely Orthodox so Bach Mozart
Beethoven Brahms I'm quite fond of
contemporary classical music or mid 20th
century anybody who isn't in the
acknowledged highest highest echelon I
don't think so I think my tastes are so
remarkably
close to what you would call Buckhannon
in these particular areas that they're
boring do you think I find a lot of
music before Bach maybe somewhat
overrated
so Palestrina is an important composer
when I listen to it I just don't enjoy
it as much as I base a post to memmio my
defect yom de Machaut it's fine
I don't know just again to pray I like
it I don't love it anything from that
period okay is fine in a slightly yeah
under impressed manner do you think I
think with Monteverdi and then Bach
things explode and become marvelous and
amazing do you think even temperament is
really the the central is that ground
zero for for the specific beauty of
western music I think it's development
of instruments through capitalism and
markets and growth of a middle-class and
having more people experiment at playing
and composing pianos become much better
string instruments become much battery
of the modern Orchestra you have actual
audiences and the interplay of those
forces as opposed to music being more in
the church maybe closer to pure vocal
music I just think it's much better and
almost everyone in their heart knows
that yeah yeah the bat tell me that no
no no I'm I'm actually I'm processing in
real excites you in classical music
I think Haydn's under somewhat
underrated closer to Mozart than people
want to admit yeah quite durable gosh I
mean I guess I saw it is amazing Peaks
but a significant portion of what Mozart
wrote is boring the younger works are
mostly boring I often feel that I have
must have a hole in my soul because of
the amount of Mozart that doesn't land
that I hear all of these people
describing Mozart is this you know exact
exactly perfect balance and there's
something about the language that I find
somewhat repellent so that I'm less
likely to get along with people who are
bananas over over Mozart they if
somebody is very clear about BA like
Bach is like heroin it's an addiction
you can't you just can't get enough of
the stuff
relate to that much more I often say
that there are mathematicians who will
claim that Bach isn't their favorite
composer and I never believed them but
you know take Mozart symphonies which
are obviously chronological 29 is quite
good and then not until you know maybe
36 you could say 33 34 but before 29
they're just boring if they were somehow
all gone I don't think there'd be any
great loss
so most of Mozart isn't that good I
don't think it detracts from him but
even with Bach there's extreme selection
which Bach you hear you don't hear most
of they can Todd is very much most of
them are boring yeah that was the main
thing he created so there's some of that
in Johann Sebastian as well you don't
exonerate him from the board and charge
altogether Christmas oratorio it's
pretty good it's not an incredible work
so even st. John's passion it's quite
good not as good as b-minor mask or st.
Matthew's passion right so there's
extreme selection in the bach you're
hearing and thinking about I mean you
know the funny thing for me is that I
had to swim upstream from Segovia's
translation of Spanish piano music on to
guitar I didn't realize that there was
an entire world of Spanish piano music
where the guitar wasn't originally
thought of necessarily as a as a concert
or art music instrument it was more of a
folk instrument and so that's been a
huge well of of interest for me like
listening to ABBA Nissan on piano is
amazing Alesha de la rocha right
she's a wonderful performer of that but
the guitar music I find it very
interesting to take some more modern
like ambient music like Brian Eno or the
whole movement from the 1970s and listen
and think through what was going on
there right and then go back to earlier
guitar music Baroque but also the
Spaniards and listen to it through that
lens and it just comes alive and a
completely new way I had that with
Robert Fripp that's a Fripp was
evocative of exactly like wailing music
yes and I've never traced down why I
felt that are you
so so we're I'm a big fan of what is
misleadingly called world music just
listening to as many different musics as
you can kind of figuring out their
logics and then going back and applying
it to what you already knew from
rock-and-roll or classical music or jazz
and seeing it all you know quite a new
re that's a very high productivity
activity are you interested in in ode
music sure of course
so like when I found linear bashir in
Iraq I just might my jaw dropped I
thought this was such gorgeous stuff and
then and I sort of made my way to
Minerva shear through a fairy dalit rush
who I think is unbelievable and
eventually I was listening in this
middle-eastern idiom and I hear him
start to play with blues and rock and
roll on the OOD and it was fascinating
watching somebody from Iraq who'd
studied in Europe of course watching you
there's a for example in at Stanford
University there's this garden which I
think has master carvings from Polynesia
Indonesia and there's versions of
rodin's gates of Hell in the thinker in
this Polynesian or Indonesian idiom and
it's just fascinating to see oneself
regarded by the other sometimes I think
the more interesting question is which
musics don't you like and to think
through those so I'm gonna ask you a
Rick why didn't use ik do you really not
like or con - and I think it's just bad
or wrong somehow I have trouble with
music that doesn't allow us to impart
more emotion because it's too highly
produced and I'm pretty sure that has to
do with the emotion because I find Jimi
Hendrix very emotional I found that
shares believe where she uses the
auto-tune function as an instrument
rather than as a correcting of the human
voice to be very emotional but when I
hear very like computer oriented or can
you name a name
what do you reject point the finger nah
geez do I have to you have to its your
podcast
I must hope the person isn't listening
well I guess there was a time when I
didn't like Amy Stuart's version of
knock on wood which was a great piano
R&B song because I found that it was so
highly overproduced that I just couldn't
cotton to it and that had to do with the
disco influence I'm choosing things now
that I really dislike but I've sort of
maybe come around because I find no look
you find something in just about
everything that you listen to it's very
hard to create music that's completely
devoid of interest and so if I spend
more time with something even if it's
really bad I'll usually be able to find
something in it that well that's why it
became famous and that's why that's why
it's being listened to I've been down on
EDM to be blunt I don't think that I've
at some point made a car ride with a
friend and I said put on songs we can
sing along with the person puts on some
EDM there was nothing close to a
campfire song inside of it I found that
kind of sad you buy into electronic
dance music sorry heavy metal I meant to
say heavy metal such as I mean there's a
lot of artistry in it so I asked to
enjoy this when I did my conversations
with Feiler podcast with him he's one of
my favorite music critics a brilliant
guy you should have him on but I asked
him at heavy metal I said underrated or
overrated and he said well it's
underrated but I couldn't get him to
admit that he actually listened to it
okay so you want to go there
I think it's underrated from technical
musicianship and I think it's often
overrated in terms of what it does to
heart Paul Gilbert that's exactly what
he said in other words okay so Paul
Gilbert has a beautiful riff on this
he's a you know obviously fantastic
guitarist but he says you can take a
great blues guitar guitarist teach them
a lot of scales and turn them into a
shredder of devoid of interest but with
fantastic technical chops I think that
that's real
sad I think that what one of the things
I'm very concerned about is the fall-off
an interest in musicianship like in
guitar at the moment we have these
fantastic guitar virtuosos who live on
YouTube and Instagram and the guitar
universe is paying attention to them but
the outside universe is not there's this
guy Guthrie Govan who lots of people I
know have never heard of this guy and
he's an unbelievable gift to the guitar
where is he what group is he part of
what are his main songs you know he can
he can be anyone and then he can be his
own thing
he's like the granite of guitar I guess
yeah but it's very odd to me that
or for example percussive guitar there's
a guy named Justin King who did a song
oddly enough called knock on wood which
just showcases how many ways you can now
interact with your instrument through
harmonics and various you know patterns
of drumming on the wood the way the
flamenco guitarists used to brought to a
high level I can't get a lot of people
interested in all of the weird
innovations that are taking place a
little bit like rodney mullen and
skateboarding where originally you're
skateboarding on four wheels and then
his point is like well okay well what
else can we do you're thinking well what
do you mean well maybe we could
skateboard on the bottom side or on the
sides of the skateboard and you're
thinking does that even make sense and
he says well sure I'll show you well
that's what percussive guitar has been
for me it told me that I didn't
understand the instrument more or less
at all something else I'm really
enthusiastic about is sugar blue on
harmonica do you know this guy not known
to me I don't know the song is it on
YouTube do you know the song miss you by
the Rolling Stone all right well that
that that harmonica is sugar blue
obviously the guy who can thread that if
you break the harmonic into three
registers he can thread the top register
like nobody's business and he and John
popper of Blues Traveler we're sort of
locked in some artistic conversation the
rest of us can barely understand like
that excites the hell out of me because
you're taking an instrument that's so
limited and you're saying Wow
it's only limited to you because you
haven't figured out what she could do
with it other than Bach maybe South
Indian classical music is the closest we
have in music to mathematics and at
times I think what he says I listen to
that because I would have said you know
whoever somehow the North Indian no the
South the Carnatic yeah I think that the
North Indian I mean look the this is
just a world that I knew nothing about
and I chanced upon this book of a
musicologist named Neal Sorrell called
something like Indian music in
performance you can find it on the
internet with lots of little sound files
that he made for a cassette way back in
the day and he took it an entire
performance of ROM Narayan the great
sarangi playin violinist man this is
just how did I not know there was an
entire universe of Indian classical
music you may be partial to the South
I'm very partial to the north but south
north along with Bach and maybe the
Beatles it has the only other serious
claim to being the best music period
all right the beatles defend yourself so
what's your take on three beatles songs
that are at least current and you're
thinking and that really show off how
deep that cannon is was it 1966 you
won't see me it's basically a paul song
but the melancholy have the background
vocals operate what's done with the
piano the bass line it operates on so
many different levels at once just
sounds like a simple ballad but every
time you listen to it there's something
new in their complex emotionally and
then it's just over you never give me
your money
the last 10 15 seconds are just
phenomenal Paul had been listening to
John Cage and Stockhausen and just sound
and what's the dividing line between
sound and music and he just sticks that
in the end of a Beatle song with a
lovely melody and the whole thing just
dissolves and then you get back to
marching through the Abbey Road side to
medley Hey Jude this is so many Beatles
songs that I think are just phenomenally
better than what other people who are
doing and they synthesize more different
parts of music than anything Bach did
that's their claim to greatness in terms
though it slows levels okay so the
needles mostly lennon-mccartney they're
composing these songs and they're
playing them and they're singing them
and they're producing them and they're
a-plus excellent in all of those
dimensions yes on their best material
and Bach was a composer probably an
excellent player we don't really know
but he was reputed to be very good easy
enough to believe the Beatles take on
and added three or four dimensions that
are not in classical music and master
them and then every album they changed
their style every song they changed
their style they hardly repeat
themselves yes they have a lot of
clunkers they had the two best voices in
rock and roll
John and Paul Monroe all right it's so
impressive all right let's have a small
fight we'll get back Aretha Franklin
when the Rolling Stones Paul she's
wonderful what would you have said she's
less first I told them that I would have
got my Freddy Mercury and Roy Orbison
where am I wrong Roy Orbison has eight
or nine amazing songs which are
incredible and the Beatles themselves
loved right but that's kind of a then
it's ready mercury sir Freddie Mercury
has one album two albums you can listen
to straight through his vocal effect is
most of the time broadly the same he's
one of the top vocalists absolutely and
I know you're partial maybe to Parsi
culture and where he comes from
drag that in but in terms of versatility
I don't think he's close to the Beatles
thank you and I love Queen and I went to
see them play not with Freddie Mercury
but with Adam Lambert who did a
fantastic job I thought I still listen
to Queen I'm a big fan but they're
totally the relational way I don't think
that's true I think that they've got
maybe two dimensions there's like the
shredder a early punk semi-metal style
well then there's the ballads I just
love my life you hurt me no I feel like
Brian May is so incredibly tasteful I
agree he doesn't have to play a note
more or less than he wants he's just not
needy and then you know Roger Taylor's
I'm
love with my car I think is one of the
most comically brilliant songs I've ever
heard so I and I don't even listen to
that much queen are you familiar with
the voice of Eva Cassidy given that you
were in the Washington area for a long
time only marginally but I've never
heard it live if that's what you're
asking
just there's an album called live at
Blues Alley where she does a version of
stormy Monday that just tears my heart
and shreds and barely puts it back
together by the end it's just
unbelievable performance of a song I
thought I've heard everybody's version
of it and just just said well you
haven't heard this one apparently she
was sick while the recording session was
happening and so some magic happened to
her voice because of the illness it's
really interesting yes Cecille Maclaurin
sulphate is my favorite jazz popular
song vocalist and she's active now I've
seen her three times I think she's
better than Ella Fitzgerald she's in her
prime she's maybe about thirty plays or
you know around in club's very often has
plenty of CDs I love Ella Fitzgerald and
never put her on why is that it's a
little exaggerated and mannered and she
was trying too hard her technique is
incredible but it's always excessively
Oh conscious of what the audience is
thinking for me you know I used to enjoy
it when I here but I also never put it I
use it as like the gold standard for
lots of things like Cole Porter and then
it's summer it is yeah I don't I I think
that there's something in my tastes that
have changed with the time and I now
just never I never reach for it you know
like Art Tatum I always enjoy when I'm
listening to his piano work but I never
think boy am I in an Art Tatum mood
because how can you be in an Art Tatum
ooh it's so exacting and demanding on
the ear that like that's not something
that happens he might have been the one
of the two greatest jazz pianists with
monk but I or Cecil Taylor well I don't
hear new things when I hear Tatum it's
just perfect right it's just it's just
and it contains every style of its time
and then some but I don't feel the need
to go back to it I'm okay with that yeah
okay gone down in my eyes but I think
whatever nobody was ever really able to
work with there's a guy named
Rick Lewis who I think I connect to
Tatum and I start to say oh well maybe
if I saw this as being part of a of a
lineage but it's there's something about
the fact that you know Hendrix didn't
really leave descendants on the guitar
and I feel like Tatum didn't really
leave descendants on the piano
well the monk really surprised some ways
he's a funny descendant of Tatum more
than you would think
monk monk he has very little technique
but the idea of integrating styles and
making jokes he was in my opinion highly
influenced by art tatum he just didn't
play the piano very well but as a
composer he's phenomenal I don't know
Don solo monk
it could be the best jazz in our album
the theory is and I still listen to it
do you ever take on the weirdness of
Miles Davis generosity to us all in
terms of leaving this beautiful legacy
and his being a complete dick well a lot
of wonderful creators have been complete
dicks there's a long list of those
Picasso some people have said John
Lennon I don't know the full list but
he's not some unusual data point to be
explained partly there might be
correlations between creativity and
having unusual brains right right and
then once you're succeeding you can get
away with a lot more and then drugs into
the equation for Davis and Lennon and
bad things happen so this is not a huge
surprise all right oh so getting back to
the Beatles okay
when Lennon writes the song was how do
you sleep right after the Beatles have
broken up he he makes a reference to
something about you didn't see Sgt
pepper's if Sgt pepper's took you by
surprise you'd better see right through
that mother's eyes yeah it means Paul
McCartney so he admits Sergeant Pepper
with Paul's album which it kind of was
that's quite an admission well is that
Paul was the workaholic in the Beatles
yeah that's the key point here so what I
hadn't understood and this is only
because I happened to weirdly be friends
with with John son Sean
is Sean points very clearly to
Strawberry Fields forever as being the
discontinuity in Lennon's ability as a
composer I agree with that what okay
how did I miss this and how do you see
that well I don't know that you missed
it I did miss it it's John's group you
look at hard day's night album there's
hardly any Paul songs on there's things
you said today which is amazing but it's
a John album and it's pretty close to
perfect even John's like first real song
please please me one of the best Beatles
songs completely visceral hits you in
the gut still sounds amazing but I think
after Strawberry Fields John stopped
innovating he had an amazing voice
emotionally which he still could use you
have songs like I am The Walrus which
have a kind of even melodic line and a
bit of pulsating but when you start to
hear John songs through the lens of a
few applied machine learning to them
there's a similar structure to a lot of
the melodies they don't move around that
much the way Paul melodies do and Paul
being the workaholic just gets better
and better and better and Paul learns
from George Martin and Paul learns
orchestration Paul even became a good
classical music composer that's
phenomenal
and by the time of Sergeant Pepper it's
Paul's group and Paul is calling the
shots Abbey Road side to is you know
basically Paul's work Paul's creation
even with the John songs a piece like
Tomorrow Never Knows which is John
singing John composed a very flat
melodic line but the whole construction
of the sound was mostly Paul and Paul
will take credit for that so it becomes
Paul's group John feels more pushed out
it's the start of the Beatles breaking
up and so on yeah so they're these
dynamics within the group that I'm not I
never actually studied the Beatles
enough but like songs like across the
universe don't really impress themselves
upon you as being it's that same kind of
even not much varying melodic line
carried by John's voice and mood and the
fact that it's the Beatles I like the
song but Paul is experimenting much more
by then and I see very interest here's
the thing about how do you sleep by John
it was I learned recently it was
actually Paul who started that phew
yeah Paul had a song to many people you
know that was your lucky break and he
was really mocking John like oh it was
lucky that you you know hung out with me
and John was retaliating people think
John is the aggressor and that but Paul
was like super passive-aggressive
alright then I want to put together a
data series and I want to get your
reaction to it so I'm gonna start with
Gilbert and Sullivan and I'm gonna have
Jagger and Richards
yeah Lennon McCartney Perry and Tyler
Aerosmith uh-huh
what the hell's going on with these
dyads that are so combustible both
really benefit from the antagonize
relationship and we end up with this
incredible music but it's it's so effing
personal well it's rivalry it's what
really motivates people yes it's the
money also of course but wanting to do
better than the other and having the
other as a mantle audience I think it
was Peter teal who had this on one of
his talks once that he has these
different images of people sitting on
the shoulder what would this person
think what would that person think I
have an Eric Weinstein and a Peter deal
sitting on my shoulder among others
right we all have Tyler coated arts so I
call it you know like phantom Eric
Weinstein or phantom Peter Thiel do you
run me an emulation what do you mean by
that I try to run you in emulation
sometimes I think about Tyler like I
start to get emotional about something
Tyler was not gonna fall for that he's
gonna be even keeled he's gonna think
about what's likely to be true
he's not going to think about how to
make the biggest splash and like I have
these rules that can't generate you and
what I consider to be your brilliance
and contribution but it can it can
generate a kind of thumbnail sketch of
you without you needing to be present oh
sure but it's harder to have a phantom
Eric Weinstein because the phantom Eric
Weinstein is about being generative and
that's harder to model than a phantom
Tyler Cowen so if you think if part of
me is even keeled even keeled might be
hard to achieve but it's not that hard
to model just like calm down all right I
can't I have
I'm so driven by passion hard to achieve
but not hard to model so you might
reject your phantom Tyler cam well
that's true one of the things I do is it
has a very strong filter which says if
the emotional register has been exceeded
by this much of that much and in either
direction Tyler wouldn't do that
call up phantom Tyler Cowen it's right
there by the phone even the real Tyler
Cameron will probably answer the phone
but you're harder to model for that
reason I'm incredibly flattered even if
that isn't your attention that yeah the
idea that you would have a hard time
doing that means a lot to me Peter is an
insanely difficult person for most of us
to model because I don't think it's even
consistent session to session Peter is
so driven by the search for something
new that whatever it is that he's
thought lasts is now incorporated into
well that's old where do we go from here
I mean it's just it's a constant part of
the model so I have my own Peter Thiel
model now you know Peter much much
better than I do but I think of it as
you really do need to incorporate
everything you know into your current
view consistently or you're failing so
your views should be a kind of random
walk because if you can predict their
direction it means you should already be
where you're headed and there's
something wrong if you're not and the
other part of my Peter Thiel model is
the way in which he is an intensely
moral thinker and how the moral element
of his thought interacts with the
cognition and strengthens it and again
you know Peter better than I do though
he's only that's the only moral human I
will retreat but that's how I modeled
Peter his moral his religious but that
but it's not just that it's how the
moral and the cognitive are integrated
you know so I'm picking up on this weird
feature so I had him as the inaugural
episode of the interview episode of the
show and I would say that one of the one
of the reactions that people have is wow
I've never seen this side of Peter and
of course I've never seen any others
I've never seen any other side of Peter
so that the the Delta between the
private and the cartoon the private
person in the cartoon character that the
media portray is got to be
one of the largest Delta's I've known
for any other human being sure yeah
anybody else do you think we're getting
wildly wrong if we go by their media
well most people I think and plenty of
these are people I don't know but my
default assumption is if they're very
well known the media is getting them
wrong right not true in all cases but
it's a better default assumption than
the opposite so I agree that that that's
true but what I'm looking for is where
is the distortion most well Charles Koch
would be an example tell me about
Charles Koch
so I have the experience people perceive
me as being somebody who's not going to
be friendly to the Koch brothers
certainly the the image of the Koch
brothers and a lot of people I respect
think very highly of the Koch brothers
and I noticed in myself that I have a
module that says anything Koch related
has to be seen as the work of the devil
like it doesn't I don't even have a
thought before the word Koch starts to
tell me that this is something I can't
even entertain which is fascinating
because of my political milieu just
noticing metacognitively Wow I didn't
install that module where did how did it
get there just to be clear Koch
foundation is a major donor to my
University and programs I've connected
with a Peter has supported some things
I've done just for our listeners Charles
I think in terms of being an executor an
integrator and synthesizer is the most
impressive human I have met as far as I
can tell no kidding that the high
returns of Koch Industries over such a
long period of time and it's not in a
sector based on a kind of like trick
well Google obviously has done very well
I don't want to call Google a trick no
net search it's a kind of natural
monopoly yeah they've done a wonderful
job since then and YouTube and all that
yes but Koch Industries has worked in
pretty competitive sectors and earned
high returns through competence and
execution and understanding and
developing processes which are
replicable on a much larger level than
the individual of Charles Koch or and
anyone else in a way that all the other
impressive people we now have not done
so that is his and their most impressive
contribution but he is a man of the
utmost integrity and to make it clear on
issues such as climate change I don't at
all agree with him but I've known
Charles for a long time he's absolutely
a straight shooter and does what he
thinks is right and is a great American
and is very much a person to be admired
Wow
and that's reason enough to invite him
onto the portal if he if you come and
there's you know plenty of things I
disagree with him about just to make a
Charlie Munger's he's somebody that you
have had interactions with I hadn't ever
met Charlie I had a dinner with Charlie
and I was very impressed by I've heard
that famillies be very tough tough
minded individual but there's a big
payoff yeah probably true yeah I don't
even know what his media reputation is
is it the opposite of that I don't know
my sense of it is that he is happy to be
overshadowed in the media by Warren
Buffett but that to those who know he's
a powerful independent mind I noticed
that in my own work relationship with
the Peter Thiel people who don't like me
well it's out there always talking about
used the word boss but your boss did
this your boss said that like they'll
really emphasize the the hierarchy which
is something that Peter has never done
bizarrely and it allowed me for a long
period of time to move somewhat more
quietly
well Peter got more of the attention and
I don't know that there isn't a version
of that at a different level with with
Munger and Buffett where Munger is known
by everybody who should know who he is
and Buffett gets most of the headlines
yeah yeah but any other like famous
famous are they're great arbitrage
opportunities with other people whose
reputations mask incredible
contributions well I don't know if it's
arbitrage because if the people are
famous they've already been doing things
right so it's not that you know but
friends come along and hire them for a
minute
like a you know Charo who used to do the
goochy goochy act was a student of
Segovia and a fabulous classical
guitarist Dolly Parton you know I'm kind
of a genius who happens to hide behind
you know a a physique that draws most of
the attention but she's she's really an
ink just incredible thinker direct
artist Oh multiple dimensions yeah who
else like this well this is a
controversial name but Michael Jackson
and I don't at all mean to excuse the
things it certainly seems he has done
but as a musical talent even before the
bad news came out he's been grossly
underappreciated getting back to the
theme of creative individuals often
having these highly problematic elements
right well this is this is this thing
that I don't know how to get at in
mathematics I think we do an
unbelievably good job of not removing
the names of despicable people from
their own work so for example I'm very
partial to the work of a guy named
Pascal Jordan in the algebra of quantum
mechanics and quantum theory who is a
committed Nazi and there are tons of
Nazis whose names are discussed along
with their work even to places like
Hebrew University where I was for a
couple of years so it's a culture that
says we don't get to choose who brings
the gifts and we don't get it to choose
whether or not we acknowledge them just
because they did something in the rest
of their life that was untoward I think
we should stop with the ex-post purges
which are in any case highly highly
selective but that said I'm never sure
what is exactly the right policy looking
forward how do we do that do you think I
don't think we figured it out when I
hear any side in that debate I think oh
they're wrong but they can't all be
wrong or maybe they are all wrong but I
don't think I have 100 my strategy for
this I'd be curious to get your take on
it
I think that we Jews should call for the
destruction of the arch of Titus that
commemorates the sacking of Jerusalem
Ursula and the carrying off of Jewish
booty by I guess Roman hands with the
idea being that this is so preposterous
that we should tear down this ancient
arch even though you know Jews have
always hated this arch sure that it will
evidence to people just how insane it is
to attempt to you know do this excision
or exercise I don't know what you want
to call it retro actively when we
obviously have a society built on
structures of oppression I don't think
it would show people that I don't think
it would be digested or interpreted
properly and here's my worry so you can
say well we're gonna have a moratorium
on canceling people in the past right
but the past and the present are not so
neatly separated and there are people
who are a part of the past but also part
of the present a number of people in
comedy but many others who are either
active or they would be active if they
would be allowed to be active and in
those cases I'm not sure what we should
do do you have a strong feeling on louis
c.k seems to be the case that a very
large number of people want to see him
return in a very large number of people
want to make sure that that does not
happen I don't know all of the details
that maybe he's done things I would find
worse than I thought but the marginal
cases I tend to believe we should allow
for rehabilitation in general I believe
in second third and additional chances
and it's striking to me how many people
in the political debate will be oh
ex-convicts you know we need to allow
them to have jobs and rehabilitate them
and welcome the back into society but
these other offenders often they're
white men right away they cannot in any
way be allowed back on the concert stage
or wherever now maybe you think they you
know ought to be working in a cafeteria
somewhere I don't know but I'm pretty
sure those emotions and intuitions are
not consistent are you conflicted
yourself I'm conflicted myself my gut
which I'm not saying is correct right
clear is for second and third chances
but I understand incentives matter as an
economist and if everyone gets you know
an N number
chances then penalties don't matter so
much so that's why I'm conflicted I was
thinking about having I keep threatening
to do this somewhere I have a list of
like 20 paradoxes which I've called the
Hilbert problems of social justice it
named after the famous mathematical
problems and that there are certain
intractable problems that have to do
with contradictory impulses where you
can show people that there's no way of
solving these puzzles but they still
insist on trying to apply these axioms
and heuristics as if they lead to a
compatible social ordering is there any
way in which people can be dissuaded
from trying to purge themselves of the
fruits of all oppression by showing them
what that would actually mean do you
think I don't know but again that the
view that we purge nothing may be
problematic as well my own podcast
series conversations with Tyler I'm
doing one in two days with the fellow
Shaka Senghor who's a convicted murderer
oh I'd love Shaka I haven't met him yet
spent 19 years in prison seven years in
solitary thirty-six times was written up
for in some way treating guards badly
has you know confessed to you know these
charges and I had to think long and hard
like should I do a podcast with Jacques
oh you're making a great decision and
that was the conclusion I arrived at but
it's still a question right
no you I found Chaka to be I mean this
I've only it's very weird I out there
all these people in my personal and
private life who are now coming up
potentially in the context of should I
have a podcast with them I think Chaka
you can ask almost any question about
his time in prison about what the
transformation has been and I think
you'll get a very credible answer I
thought I found him incredibly
thoughtful as a theorist about the
entire system that's also my sense but
the question of does the fact that we
can learn from someone in any way
exonerate them I would still say I don't
have a clear answer but that's true but
I guess this matters for me at the
margin for selfish reasons it matters
I'm really looking forward to talking
with Shaka but if you try to generalize
I don't know where we're left so let me
give a really clean example because the
person is no longer with us and I think
that the artistic contribution is more
fascinating than we care to admit have
you ever heard the song by Charles
Manson called look at your game girl
I've heard that there are songs by
Charles Manson but I've never heard it I
don't think so I struggle with this
because it's an incredibly beautiful
performance to my ear and the human
being who created it is obviously almost
synonymous with a level of madness and
depravity that we wish to insulate
ourselves from I don't know how to
reconcile that because I I see the
sensitivity and the gift and my feeling
about it as a song if you could just
disembody it I mean be a great song if
you actually think about what it is that
you're choosing to promote this is not a
very famous song because of its
association I think it would be a huge
disservice if its popularity came to
have us reevaluate its author when the
John Lennon song run for your life comes
on the radio which is a song about
wife-beating it seems I do actually
change the channel I'm not sure I'm
consistent anybody bothers me and that's
John Lennon and I don't want to listen
are we not entitled to some hypocrisy I
mean like well I but we need optimal
hypocrisy well you need a kind of
consistently inconsistent optimal
hypocrisy and no one's found that well I
really like that cuz I I feel that I
can't get through a day without my
hypocrisy and people are always trying
to take it away from me and all I really
want to do is to minimize it and to make
sure that it's functional rather than
just a complete dodge but we also need
some hypocritical sanctions against
hypocrisy so there are multiple layers
so yeah right so you can't just sit
content in your hypocracy even if it's
optimal Tyler I could have
you here for the rest of time can I
instead say that you were welcome to
come back anytime
I would in fact love to talk to you
about gage theory and other matters of
how do we push the economics profession
forward but you know there are a million
topics I could talk to you about have
absolutely nothing to do with our area
of professional overlap will you
consider coming back I would love to
come back and I'm still planning on
having you on my podcast which we
absolutely will do and might have even
happened now if you hadn't invited me
onto yours well I I would be completely
honored may be a fantastic adventure so
thanks very much for that and let's make
that happen
Eric it's been a great pleasure oK
you've been through the portal with our
guest professor Tyler Cowen make sure
that you subscribe to this podcast on an
apple stitcher Spotify or wherever you
listen to podcasts and go over to
YouTube and try to find our channel and
make sure that you subscribe and click
the bell to be notified when our next
episode drops
thanks very much be well
[Music]